Mordecai Family papers
Mordecai Family papers
1822-1899
Mordecai Family.
0.3 linear feet
Letters and memorabilia of a North Carolina family. Correspondents include Sara Hays Mordecai, Alfred Mordecai, Miriam Gratz, Mary C. Longstreet, Sara Miley, and George C. Richards.
149323
Biographical History
The Mordecais were a prominent North Carolina family. Alfred Mordecai, the family's most well-known member, was a distinguished engineer and soldier in the U.S. Army. After graduating first in his class at West Point, he was commissioned a second lieutenant in 1823. In 1825 he became assistant engineer in charge of construction at Fort Monroe, Virginia, and he went on to become assistant to the chief of engineers. He was commissioned captain in the ordnance department upon its creation in 1832. Mordecai commanded two arsenals and became a member of the ordnance board. In 1854 he was commissioned major in the ordnance department. He visited Mexico and the Crimea, and authored numerous technical papers.
On the outbreak of the Civil War, Mordecai decided that he could not fight for either side so he resigned from the Army in May of 1861 and became a teacher of mathematics in Philadelphia. In 1863 he became assistant engineer of the Mexico and Pacific Railroad, and from 1867-1887 was treasurer and secretary of canal and coal companies controlled by the Pennsylvania Railroad Company.
Alfred Mordecai married Sara Hays in 1836. They had six children, one of whom (Alfred Mordecai, Jr.) fought for the Union during the Civil War.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mordecai Family Papers consist of approximately forty items of correspondence and a few pieces of memorabilia. These papers date from 1822-1899.
Correspondence contains only two letters from Alfred; his wife Sara is the most frequent correspondent. Other members of the Mordecai family are also represented. An index to the correspondence appears at the end of this finding aid.
Memorabilia includes newspaper clippings on Alfred Mordecai's death, a marriage certificate, and a photograph of Sara Hays Mordecai. Also present is a legend of a map of St. Petersburg, Russia, autographed by Alfred Mordecai.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. An index to the correspondence appears at the end of this finding aid.
Subject and Genre Headings
Correspondence.; Photoprints.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Some material purchased, 1963; some transferred from Kohen Collection, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1822 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1829 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1835 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1837 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1840 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1846 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1847 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1865 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1883 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1886 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1891 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1896-1899; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Envelopes (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Explication du Plan de St. Petersbourg, 1853 (Box 1)
  - Marriage certificate, Sarah H. Mordecai, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1886-1887 (Box 1)
  - Photograph, Sarah H. Mordecai, undated (Box 1)
Selected index to correspondence
Index is alphabetical by sender.
---, ---undated, Philadelphia, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, ---, ---
---, Ellen 1837 Jun 11, Peterburg, Virginia, to Alfred Mordecai
---, Julia 1837 Jan 22, Richmond, to Sarah Hays Mordecai
---, Rosa 1837 Sep 23, Philadelphia, to Sarah Hays Mordecai
----, Sally undated, Leavenworth, to Sara Hays Mordecai
B---, S--- 1846 Mar 10, Copenhagen (Denmark), to Sarah Hays Mordecai
E---, Ellen Hays 1829 Mar 3, ---, to Sarah Hays Mordecai 1835 Sep 22, Philadelphia, to Sarah Hays Mordecai
Edwards, J.L. 1847 Sep 18, Washington, D.C., to Mordecai P. Hunnicutt
Gratz, Miriam undated, Philadelphia, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, Saratoga, New York, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, Georgetown, S.C., to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, New York, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, New York, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, New York, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, ---, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, ---, to Sarah Hays Mordecai undated, ---, to Sarah Hays Mordecai
Lazarus, M.E. 1837 Jun 30, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Alfred Mordecai
Lee, I.F. 1865 Mar 10, Maryland, to Alfred Mordecai
Longstreet, Mary 1886 Jan 3, Summerville, to Alfred Mordecai 1886 Jan 14, Summerville, to Alfred Mordecai 1886 Jan 4, Summerville, to "Young Friends" 1891 Mar 30, "Hillside," Augusta, Georgia, to "Young Ladies"
Miley, J.D. 1897 Feb 9, Presidio, California, to Rosa Mordecai 1899 Feb 5, ----, to Rosa Mordecai
Miley, Sara 1898 Apr 28, Ft. Mason, California, to Rosa Mordecai
Mordecai, Alfred 1822 Jul 30, Spring Farm, Richmond, Virginia, to George C. Richards 1840 Jun 16, Birmingham, to "Madam"
Mordecai, E. 1837 Jun 11, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Alfred Mordecai
Mordecai, Laura 1837 Jun 11, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Alfred Mordecai
Mordecai, Rebecca 1837 Jun 12, Richmond, Virginia, to Alfred Mordecai
Mordecai, Rosa 1896 Feb 17, Presidio, California, to Laura Mordecai [?]
Mordecai, S. 1837 Jun 11, Peterburg, Virginia, to Alfred Mordecai
Mordecai, Sally undated, West Point, New York, to Sara Hays Mordecai
Mordecai, Sara Hays undated, West Point, New York, to Sally Mordecai 1883, Watervliet Arsenal, West Troy, New York, to "My Dear Daughter"
Whention, J.O. 1865 Mar 7, ----, to Alfred Mordecai